Guide to the James J. McDonnell transportation collection, 1939-1995
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
James J. McDonnell transportation collection
1939-1995
George Mason University. Special Collections and Archives.
James J. McDonnell
C0104
6 linear feet (9 boxes
The McDonnell collection contains materials related to McDonnell's work on the Shirley Highway project and other materials from his work at the United States Bureau of Public Roads (BPR) and Federal Highway Administration (FHWA). Types of materials include correspondence, reports, government publications, black-and-white photographs, and 35mm black-and-white negatives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Collection donated by Laurie McDonnell through John Gifford in February 1996.
Biographical Information
Born in 1930, James McDonnell worked as a civil engineer for the Army Corps of Engineers in the 1950s, then built an extensive career as a highway engineer for the Bureau of Public Roads (which would become the Federal Highway Administration). During his 33-year career with U.S. government transportation agencies, McDonnell was recognized as a national expert in transportation data collection and use. In the late 1950s and early 1960s, he directed the Shirley Highway corridor study in Northern Virginia. His study led to the widening of the four-lane, World War II-era freeway into the first freeway with reversible high-occupancy-vehicle (HOV) lanes in the median. In 1964, McDonnell was called back to Washington to fill a key vacancy as Chief of BPR's Planning Procedure Branch. During his 20-year tenure in this position, he became nationally recognized for his many accomplishments, one of which was the development of a new Home Interview Survey Manual, that brought the practice of conducting surveys, and analyzing results into the computer age. He died in 1995.
Scope and Content
The McDonnell collection contains materials related to McDonnell's work on the Shirley Highway project and other materials from his work at the US Bureau of Public Roads (BPR) and Federal Highway Administration (FHWA). Types of materials include correspondence, reports, government publications, black-and-white photographs, and 35mm black-and-white negatives.
Series 1: Printed Materials contains studies, reports, correspondence, and conference proceedings on highway and urban transportation planning mostly in the Washington, D.C., metropolitan area. Included are statistical studies of the Public Roads Administration from the 1940s, reports on a Pentagon area transportation study from 1960-61, several Fairfax, Virginia household surveys from 1986, and McDonnell's 1958 Master's thesis, "Characteristics of Traffic on a 3 Lane One-Way Roadway Entering a 2 Lane Constriction."
Series 2: Photographs contains photographs, negatives, and presentation slides of various junctures on the northbound and southbound routes of Shirley Memorial Highway. Some of the pohotgraphs show heavy traffic on Shirley Highway and the bridge leading to US 1.
Series 3: Oversize contains oversized printed materials including transportation studies and reports. Some of the reports include maps of roadways in the National Capital Region and charts and graphs of traffic patterns.
Arrangement
This collection is divided into three series according to media format. Each series is arranged by subject.
Series 1: Printed Materials, 1939-1995 (Boxes 1-5)
Series 2: Photographs, 1949-1960 (Boxes 6-7)
Series 3: Oversize, 1959-1967 (Boxes 8-9)
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives also holds many other.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
United States. Bureau of Public Roads.; United States. Federal Highway Administration.
Geographical Names:
Henry G. Shirley Memorial Highway (Va.)--Photographs.
Subjects:
Highway engineering--United States.; Transportation--United States--Planning.
Document Types:
Negatives.; Photographic prints.
Contents List
- Series 1: Printed Materials, 1939-1995; 5 boxes
  This series contains studies, reports, correspondence, and conference proceedings on highway and urban transportation planning mostly in the Washington, DC metropolitan area. Included are statistical studies of the Public Roads Administration from the 1940s, reports on a Pentagon area transportation study from 1960-61, several Fairfax, Virginia household surveys from 1986, and McDonnell's 1958 Master's thesis, "Characteristics of Traffic on a 3 Lane One-Way Roadway Entering a 2 Lane Constriction."
  - Publications by J. J. McDonnell, 1986, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Paper list of publications by McDonnell and summary of travel surveys
  - Census Data and Urban Transportation Planning in the 1980s, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Use of Census Data in Urban Transportation Planning, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Report of a conference held July 9-10, 1970
  - Analysis of Urban Highway Needs, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Graying of America and Its Implications for Travel, September 1, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Supply and Use of the Nation's Urban Highways, June 1988 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Draft
  - Continuing Transportation Planning Data Requirements, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Prepared for a Highway Research Board Conference, June 9-10, 1970
  - Demand: Populations, Households, Employment ..., ca. 1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Review of Paper: "Things Won't Get a Lot Worse: The Future of US Traffic Congestion,", 1990 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Travel Characteristics in Urban Areas; Forecasting for Highways, 1958, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Highway Research Board, Bulletins 203 and 257, facsimile
  - Tri-State Transportation Study: Home Interview Survey, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Thesis Original: Development of Capacity Factors for Lane 2 in Construction, ca. 1958 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Includes photographs and map of Queens County Grand Central Expressway
  - Thesis Equipment and Data, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - BHT Thesis Analysis, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Characteristics of Traffic on a 3 Lane One-Way Roadway Entering a 2 Lane Constriction, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - National Trends: Population, Employment and Vehicle Ownership, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - National Data Sources and Their Usefulness to Metro Area Planners, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Reflections on the Passenger Flow Survey: Issues as Developed by by Phil Fulton, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Report of the Association of Public Data Users Conference (APDU), 1986 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - List of Macdonald's Speeches (Box 2, Folder 1)
    List of speeches by highway planner Thomas H. Macdonald from 1919 to 1952
  - National Conference on Decennial Census Data for Transportation Planning, 1984, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Shirley Highway, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Pentagon Area Transportation Study, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Contains two photographs mounted on paper
  - Pentagon Area Transportation Study, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Pentagon Area Transportation Study, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Pentagon Area Transportation Study, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Pentagon Area Transportation Study, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Pentagon Area Transportation Study, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Washington Bypass Study, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Virginia Department of Transportation (VDOT)
  - Virginia Shirley Highway Improvement - Preliminary Engineering, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - New Jersey Citizens Highway Committee, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - The NCTA Plan for Transportation, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Traffic Forecasting and Origin-Destination Trip Assignment Techniques, 1958, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Use of the Telephone in Gathering Data in Transportation Studies, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Bias Control of a Bus-Rider Origin-Destination Postcard Survey, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Cost-Saving Techniques for Collection and Analysis of Origin-Destination Survey Data, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - The Ohio Procedure ... New Concepts in Home Interviews and Automatic Zoning for Origin-Destination Studies, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Cleveland
  - Computer Coding of Origins and Destinations, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - 1986 Household Survey Special Report on Income, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    County of Fairfax, Virginia
  - 1986 Household Survey Special Report on Rental Housing, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - 1986 Household Survey Special Report on Household Size, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - 1986 Household Survey Special Report on Employment, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - 1986 Household Survey Special Report on Households with Children, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - 1986 Household Survey Special Report on Age, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 1986 Household Survey Special Report on Mobility, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Recent Origin-Destination Surveys and Data Collection in North Carolina, ca. 1987 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Sampling Strategies for Small Sample Surveys, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Metropolitan Planning for Land Use and Transportation, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Toll Roads and Free Roads, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Evolution of Urban Transportation Planning, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Work of the Pulbic Roads Administration, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Work of the Public Roads Administration, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Public Roads Administration, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Public Roads Administration, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Twentieth-Century Experience in Urban Transit, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Highway Statistics, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    Public Roads Administration
  - Transportation for Urban America, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Highways, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    Report
  - Changes in Mobility in American Cities, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Highways and Urban Development, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Variation of Driver Characteristics at Intersections (Box 4, Folder 18)
    Unpublished study
  - National Highway Needs Study: Nature of Urban Transportation Problem, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Express Highways in the United States, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Highway Travel Forecasts, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Private Sector Involvement in Virginia's Nineteenth Century Transportation Improvement Program, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Changes in Urban Areas, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Rapid Transit in the United States, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Review of Papers for Theme II: Urban Transportation and Its Future, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Highway Needs After 1972, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Urban Transportation Planning Procedure, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Special Reports on Major Business Problems, ca. 1964 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Transportation Data Needs: Programs for a New Era, Proceedings of a Conference, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Recommendations for the South Leg Freeway Alignment; Recommendations for a Freeway in the Northern Sector; Recommended action on North Leg Freeway, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    District of Columbia Department of Highways and Traffic,
  - Rail Rapid Transit for the Nation's Capital, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - The Regional Development Guide, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    National Capital Regional Planning Council
  - Public Roads, a Journal for Highway Research, Vol. 30, No. 7, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Transportation Planning in the District of Columbia, 1955-1965, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Secretary Skinner Salutes James McDonnell on Veterans Day, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Series 2: Photographs, 1949-1970s; 2 boxes
  This series contains photographs, negatives, and presentation slides of various junctures on the northbound and southbound routes of Shirley Memorial Highway. Some of the pohotgraphs show heavy traffic on Shirley Highway and the bridge leading to US 1.
  - Shirley Highway - H Road Southbound from Ridge Road to US 1, 1960 (Box 6, Page 1-9)
  - Mt. Vernon Highway - Alexandria to Key Bridge, 1960 (Box 6, Page 10-21)
  - Shirley Highway - H Road Southbound from Ridge Road to US 1, 1960 (Box 6, Page 21-23)
  - End of B Road from Arlington Blvd. to Memorial Bridge, 1960 (Box 6, Page 23-26)
  - Shirley Highway - H Road Northbound from US 1 to Ridge Road, 1960 (Box 6, Page 27-29)
  - Start of Shirley Highway Northbound from Rt. 7 to 14th St. Bridge, 1960 (Box 6, Page 30-35)
  - End of Shirley Highway Southbound, 1960 (Box 6, Page 35-41)
  - Miscellaneous photographs, mostly of Shirley Highway, 1960 (Box 6, Page 41-63)
    Photos show highway and bridge traffic
  - Shirley Highway and Rt. 1, 1949-1952 (Box 7, Page 1-3)
    5" x 7" photographs
  - Shirley Highway, 1950-1952 (Box 7, Page 4-24)
    8.5" x 11" photos of highway traffic in different weather conditions
  - Shirley Highway, ca. 1950-1960 (Box 7, Page 25-27)
    Negatives
  - Images from presentations on transportation planning, 1960s-1970s (Box 7, Page 28-34)
    Slides; includes dozens of slides for DC area studies and 91 slides from Upstate New York studies "for Crighton's AASHO talk at Portland, Oregon"
- Series 3: Oversize, 1959-1968; 2 boxes
  This series contains oversized printed materials including transportation studies and reports. Some of the reports include maps of roadways in the National Capital Region and charts and graphs of traffic patterns.
  - The Region's Growth, May 1967 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Regional Plan Association
  - Urban Transit Development in Twenty Major Cities, March 1968 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    Automotive Safety Foundation
  - What Freeways Mean to Your City, January 1964 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Urban Freeway Development, August 1964 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Washington Metropolitan Area Transportation Study, Vol. 4: A Recommended Highway Improvement Program, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    Regional Highway Planning Committee
  - Public Participation in Regional Planning, October 1967 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Baltimore Area Mass Transportation Plan: Phase II-Long-Range Program, October 1965 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    Metropolitan Transit Authority of Maryland
  - Henry G. Shirley Memorial Highway Improvement: Bus Facility Study, September 1964 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    Commonwealth of Virginia Department of Highways
  - F.A.I Route 95 Cost Summary Sheets (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Henry G. Shirley Memorial Highway Improvement: Preliminary Engineering Report, July 1962 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Transportation Plan: National Capital Region, The Mass Transportation Survey Report, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    National Capital Planning Commission, National Capital Regional Planning Council
  - Atlas of New York City: Five Boroughs, No.1445 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Mass Transportation Survey National Capital Region: Civil Engineering Report, January 1959 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Mass Transportation Survey National Capital Region:Traffic Engineering Study, 1958 (Box 9, Folder 6)